<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- Copyright 2002-2008 CS Communication & Systèmes
  Licensed to CS Communication & Systèmes (CS) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  CS licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Orekit Changes</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="4.0" date="TBD"
             description="TBD">
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix">
        The ephemeris produced by numerical propagator now checks date validity in
        propagate method.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        The EME2000/J2000 frame was slightly mis-oriented (about 20 milli arcseconds).
        It really was the GCRF frame. This has been fixed and now both the GCRF and
        the EME2000/J2000 are available.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Dates in UTC within leap seconds are now displayed correctly (i.e. a 61st
        second is added to the minute).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="quinput">
        Fixed an overflow error in AbsoluteDate that generated an exception when any
        attempts was made to print dates far away like AbsoluteDate.JULIAN_EPOCH or
        AbsoluteDate.MODIFIED_JULIAN_EPOCH.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Changed test configuration to always use a new JVM for each test. This prevents
        some false positive to be generated.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The low accuracy Sun model based on Newcomb theory and the Moon model based
        on Brown theory have been withdrawn as they are superseded by the support of JPL
        DE 405 binary ephemerides files.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The ThirdBody abstract class has been removed and its specific method
        getMu has been moved up into CelestialBody interface and
        renamed getGM.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Improved external data configuration. Now two different properties can be
        used to define both a filesystem-located and a classpath-located data
        directories trees. This allows easy roll-out of system-wide configuration
        data that individual users can override, and also allows embedding data for
        autonomous configuration.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Renamed the iers package into data, as it is not IERS specific anymore. Some
        classes where also moved out of the package and into the frame and time
        package and their visibility reduced to package only. This improves decoupling
        and reduces clutter on users by limiting the number of visible classes.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The performance of IAU-2000 precession-nutation model computation has been
        tremendously improved, using a combined caching and interpolation approach. The
        simplified model (which was quite inaccurate in version 3.1) has therefore been
        removed as it was not needed anymore.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The ITRF 2005 frame is now supported instead of the older ITRF 2000 frame. The
        Earth Orientation Parameters data handling classes have been updated to match
        this change and read the new file format provided by IERS.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The J2000 frame has been renamed as EME2000 as this name seems to be more
        widely accepted and reduces confusion with the J2000.0 epoch. The
        Frame.getJ2000() method is still available, but has been deprecated
        and will be removed in the future.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Changed TimeScale from base abstract class to interface only.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Renamed some classes for better understanding: ChunkedDate is now DateComponents,
        ChunkedTime is now TimeComponents, ChunksPair is now DateTimeComponents. The
        getChunks method from AbsoluteDate as also been renamed into getComponents accordingly.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Espen Bj&#248;rntvedt">
        Added norse localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Francesco Coccoluto">
        Added italian localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Derek Surka">
        Added support for mean motion first and second derivatives fields in TLE.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to rebuild the two lines of TLE instances.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Derek Surka">
        Added constructor from already parsed elements for TLE.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a method to retrieve a body-centered inertial frame to the
        CelestialBody interface. As a consequence, thirteen new frames are
        predefined: Sun, Moon, planets and barycenters provided by JPL binary
        ephemerides.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Support for the JPL DE 405 and DE 406 binary ephemerides files has been added
        and a factory class SolarSystemBody uses these files to provide implementations
        of the CelestialBody interface for Sun, Moon, the eight solar system
        planets,the Pluto dwarf planet as well as the solar system barycenter and Earth-Moon
        barycenter points.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        The CelestialBody interface now provides velocity as well as position.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        A getCalls() method has been added to the NumericalPropagator class to count the
        number of calls to the differential equations computation method. This helps
        tuning the underlying integrator settings in order to improve performances.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        A lot more classes and interfaces are now serializable, to help users embed
        instance in their own serializable classes.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added predefined leap seconds to allow proper turn-key use of the library
        even without an already configured environment. All known leap seconds at
        time of writing (2008) are predefined, from 1972-01-01 to 2009-01-01 (the
        last one has been announced in Bulletin C 36 on 2008-07-04 and is not yet
        present in the UTC-TAI.history published file)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved user-friendliness of the time-scales by changing methods parameters
        types to more easily understandable ones.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved user-friendliness of the AbsoluteDate class by adding several
        new constructors and methods for common cases. It is in particular now possible
        to use offsets within a time scale, for example to build a date given as a
        fractional number of days since a reference date in UTC, explicitly ignoring
        intermediate leap seconds.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved the class handling date/time components: added a constructor to allow building
        from an offset with respect to a reference epoch, implemented Comparable interface and
        added equals and hashCode methods.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved the class handling date components: added a constructor to allow building
        from any reference epoch, not only J2000.0 (thus simplifying use of modified julian day),
        added getMJD() method, added several constants JULIAN_EPOCH, MODIFIED_JULIAN_EPOCH,
        FIFTIES_EPOCH, GPS_EPOCH, J2000_EPOCH and JAVA_EPOCH.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a new time scale: GPSScale.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added the changes page to the generated site.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="3.1" date="2008-07-16"
             description="This release is the first public release of Orekit."/>
  </body>
</document>
