<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- Copyright 2002-2010 CS Communication & Systèmes
  Licensed to CS Communication & Systèmes (CS) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  CS licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Orekit Changes</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="5.1" date="TBD"
             description="TBD.">
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added the UT1, TCB and GMST time scales used in CCSDS Orbit Data Messages
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an error in JPL ephemerides: they are in TDB time scale
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed UTC time scale between 1961-01-01 and 1971-12-31 ; in this time range
        the offset between UTC and TAI was piecewise linear
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        completed support for CCSDS Time Code Format (CCSDS 301.0-B-3) ; now in addition
        to ASCII Calendar Segmented Time Code which has been supported for a while,
        Orekit also supports CCSDS Unsegmented Time Code (CUC), CCSDS Day Segmented
        Time Code (CDS) and CCSDS Calendar Segmented Time Code (CCS)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a freeze method to Transform, to remove time-dependent parts
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an out of memory error when lots of temporary frames were created in loops
        and discarded
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        use the new FastMath class from commons-math instead of the standard java.util.Math
        class for increased accuracy and speed
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added support for the new bulletinB data published by Paris-Meudon observatory
        for IAU-1980 precession-nutation model (IERS has ceased publishing bulletinB
        files for both IAU-1980 precession-nutation model and IAU-2000
        precession-nutation model as of early 2010).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added support for the new XML files containing both bulletinA and bulletinB data
        published by IERS (both the finals and daily files are supported).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Orekit now depends on at least version 2.2 of Apache commons-math
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a way to list what data have been loaded through DataProvidersManager
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        PropagationException can now be created directly from OrekitException, thus simplifying
        wrapping lower Orekit errors in step handlers
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        improved exception propagation from low level java runtime and Apache commons-math libraries
        preserving initial error stack trace
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        changed exception localization framework to simplify messages handling
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        greatly improved AbsoluteDate accuracy by shifting epoch when needed and separating
        long/double computations to avoid too large offsets and numerical cancellations, it is
        now possible to still have an absolute date accurate to about 1.0e-13s after shifting
        it 10000 times by 0.1s steps
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an error in TopocentricFrame.getPVCoordinates: the coordinates returned were not the
        coordinates of the topocentric frame origin with respect to the specified frame, but were the
        coordinates of the specified frame origin with respect to the topocentric frame.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an errors in data loading in tutorials when one of the path in the classpath
        contained a space
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        improved CelestialBodyPointed attitude mode: the spin now correctly includes
        the coupling effect of the phasing reference
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an error in SpinStabilized attitude mode: the spin was reversed
        with respect to the specification
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        added a GroundMaskElevationDetector dealing with local physical mask for visibility
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        added an ApparentElevationDetector taking refraction into account in a terrestrial
        environment
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="update">
        enhanced DateDetector behaviour to allow adding new event dates on the fly
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix" due-to="Derek Surka">
        fixed an error in FramesFactory when getting ITRF2005 and TIRF2000 frames:
        ignoreTidalEffects was handled wrong.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an error in LofOffset attitude mode: the computed attitude was reversed
        with respect to the specification
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added an AttitudesSequence class which can handle several laws, only one of
        which being active at any time. The active law changes as switch events are
        triggered. This can be used for example to alternate between daylight attitude mode
        and eclipse attitude mode, or between normal observing mode and special modes
        for ground contact or maneuvers.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix" due-to="Bruno Revelin">
        fixed an error when crawling a classpath or a directory a zip file was found.
        This might lead to select an inappropriate data provider.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="5.0" date="2010-05-06"
             description="version 5.0 is a major release of Orekit. It introduces several new
             features and bug fixes. Some slight incompatibilities with respect to previous
             versions have been introduced, but they should be easy to overcome to users. Users
             are strongly advised to upgrade to this version. The major points introduced in version
             5.0 are a very general PVCoordinatesProvider interface, a new shiftedBy method allowing
             many time-dependent instances (AbsoluteDate, Orbit, PVCoordinates, Attitude and SpacecraftState)
             to be slightly shifted in time using simple evolution models (keplerian for orbit, fixed
             angular rate for attitude, fixed translation for position/velocity), a redesign of the
             attitude interfaces and an experimental (read subject to change) numerical propagator
             able to compute jacobians of the state with respect to both initial state and force
             models parameters. Version 5.0 now depends on version 2.1 of Apache commons math.">
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        a new experimental numerical propagator has been added, in addition to computing
        the spacecraft state at target time, it also computes the partial derivatives of
        this state with respect to the initial state (one jacobian) and with respect to
        models parameters (another jacobian). The jacobians are integrated alongside with
        the state, using variational equations for better accuracy and numerical robustness.
        This will help further implementation of orbit determination or optimization
        algorithms. This code is still considered to be experimental as of 5.0 and the API
        could change in the future.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        a new SpacecraftFrame class has been added, taking into account orbit and
        attitude thanks to an underlying propagator. This allows to see the spacecraft just
        as another known geometrical object automatically handled and connected to all
        other frames. For an instantaneous view, Transform instances can also be built
        directly by SpacecraftState instances.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        frames can now be flagged as quasi-inertial or not; only quasi-inertial frames
        are suitable for defining orbits
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        the Topocentric frame now provides a way to retrieve the body shape on which the
        frame is defined
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="update">
        changed the way Veis 1950 frame is constructed.
        Now, its parent is the PEF frame with no EOP corrections applied.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="John Pritchard">
        fixed a parameters inversion in Earth Orientation Parameters for IAU-1980 models.
        The error could introduce up to a few meters error in position during transformations
        between TEME and MEME
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        factories have been introduced for handling all data formats. Their default configuration
        correspond to the legacy formats used in previous versions (IERS format for UTC-TAI, EOPC04
        and bulletins B for Earth Orientation Parameters, JPL format for celestial bodies ...).
        Users can now add support for their own formats if they want (for example if they prefer
        using bulletins A instead of EOPC04 and bulletins B, or if they have their own gravity
        field format ...). Consequences of these changes are that the SolarSystemBody and
        the PotentialReaderFactory classes have been deprecated (replaced by CelestialBodyFactory and
        GravityFieldFactory) and that TimeScalesFactory and FramesFactory have been extended. All these
        factories follow the same generic pattern.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        improved thread safety (however, Orekit is still NOT completely thread-safe).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        the loaders for gravity fields now can optionally allow missing coefficients (they will be
        replaced by 0.0 except c[0][0] which will be replaced by 1.0).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        the loader for gravity fields in the ICGEM format now support empty lines in the file
        (there is for example one blank line at the end of the file in the orekit-data zip archive).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added support for the GRGS gravity field files formats.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added a way to list the available satellite numbers in TLE files.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        improved TLE elements loading. Now TLE lines are loaded using the standard data loading
        mechanism (thus allowing loading from disk files, network, classpath ...), they can
        contain TLE for several objects in one file, and they may contain some non-TLE lines
        if desired.
      </action>
      <action dev="v&#233;ronique" type="add" >
        a new PVCoordinatesProvider interface has been created on top of several existing classes
        and interfaces (orbit propagator, celestial bodies, some moving frames ...). This is a
        major generalization that allows to use either satellites or celestial bodies in many
        algorithms (attitude pointing target, eclipses and field of view events ...)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        improved numerical propagator efficiency when used from an outside loop: the initial
        state is automatically set to the last state at propagation end, thus allowing to
        restart from here without recomputing everything
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added a reset feature in all propagators, allowing to reuse an already configured
        propagator for several different orbits
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed a mode handling error in NumericalPropagator: when a propagator was reused
        with a new mode setting, the previous step handlers were still used in addition to
        the new ones instead of replacing them
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed an interpolation error for orbits crossing the -PI/+PI singularity between
        entries in the Ephemeris class
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        KeplerianPropagator now preserve orbits types
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        AbsoluteDate, Orbit, PVCoordinates, Attitude and SpacecraftState instances can now all
        be slightly shifted in time using simple evolution models (keplerian for orbit, fixed
        angular rate for attitude, fixed translation for position/velocity). This is not a
        replacement for proper propagation but is useful for known simple motions or small
        time shifts or when coarse accuracy is sufficient
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        changed AttitudeLaw.getState signature to use complete orbit. This is an incompatible
        change introduced to fix a major bug in spin computation for some attitude laws. The laws
        for which orientation depends on satellite velocity have a spin vector that depends on
        acceleration. This can be computed only if complete orbit is available. This change
        should be simple to handle from a users point of view, as the caller generally already
        has the orbit available and attitude laws implementations can retrieve all the former
        parameters (date, position/velocity, frame) directly from orbit.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed spin rate computation errors in almost all attitude modes
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added a new simple linear attitude mode: FixedRate
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed an error in event detection: when two events were very close (for example a very
        short ground station visibility), the second one may be ignored despite the first one
        was detected.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed corner cases in event detection during orbit propagation, sometimes
        an already detected and handled event prevented the propagator to go further in time.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added an EventShifter wrapper allowing to slightly shift raw events in time. This is useful
        for example to switch an attitude mode from solar pointing to something else a few minutes
        before eclipse entry and going back to solar pointing mode a few minutes after eclipse exit.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        added a new AlignmentDetector.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add" >
        added a new EclipseDetector handling either umbra or penumbra entry and exit events.
      </action>
      <action dev="v&#233;ronique" type="add" >
        added new CircularFieldOfViewDetector and DihedralFieldOfViewDetector handling
        field of view entry and exit events for any type of target.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added an experimental implementation of a BoxAndSolarArray spacecraft model considering a convex
        body (either parallelepipedic or defined by a set of facets) and a rotating solar array, for
        accurate modeling of surface forces with attitude. Beware that this class is still considered
        experimental, so use it with care!
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        completely changed the RadiationSensitive and DragSensitive interfaces to be more comprehensive
        and handle properly lift and side force effects when used with non-symmetric spacecrafts/flux geometry
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Christelle Blandin">
        fixed denormalization of gravity field coefficients, the last coefficient
        was not initialized
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added a relative constructor and a getMomentum method to PVCoordinates
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a special implementation improving performances for the frequent case of identity transform
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed forgotten radians to degrees conversions for inclination and RAAN in CircularOrbit.toString()
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a Constants interface including a few useful physical constants.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a way to build date components from week components (this can be used
        for scheduled operations with week-related periods)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added string parsing features for dates and times components supporting ISO-8601 formats
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Orekit is now packaged as an OSGi bundle
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        added some pieces of an UML model for the library (available in the source distribution)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        updated error message localization to be more consistent with Java exception. Now getMessage
        returns a non-localized message and only getLocalizedMessage returns a message localized for
        the platform default locale. A new getMessage(Locale) method has also been added to
        retrieve the message in any desired locale, not only the platform default one. The messages
        are also built and translated only when needed, so if an exception is triggered and
        never displayed, the message will never be built.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="4.1" date="2009-08-18"
             description="version 4.1 is an upgrade bringing some new features and fixing a
             few bugs. The equinox-based frames family with IAU1980 precession-nutation
             models that are still used by many legacy systems are now supported. This
             simplifies interoperability with legacy systems and helps migrating from this
             old frames family to the new CIO-based ones that is supported by orekit since its
             first versions. The data loading mechanism used to retrieve IERS data (Earth
             Orientation Parameters, UTC-TAI history) and JPL ephemerides is now also used
             to retrieve gravity potential files. This mechanism has also been vastly improved
             to support new use cases (loading from disk, from classpath, from network delegating
             loading to an external library ...). Another change is the addition of the TDB
             time scale. Some minor incompatibilities have been introduced but they are easy
             to solve for users, the explanations are provided in detailed changes report.">
      <action dev="aude" type="add" >
        added TDB time scale
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        the RadiationSensitive and DragForce interfaces now have an
        additional SpacecraftState parameter in all their get methods.
        This allows to implement models that take into account solar
        arrays rotation. Note that this changes breaks compatibility
        for users that did add their own implementations, but it is
        simple to deal with (simply add one parameter in the signature
        and ignore it) so its was considered acceptable.
       </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="James Housden">
        added german localization for error messages
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        added a feature allowing all tests to clear the already built reference
        objects (frames, time scales, solar system bodies ...) between each tests,
        thus removing the need to launch tests in separate JVMS. This allows to
        launch all tests directly from eclipse, and this speeds up maven tests by
        a factor 4 at least
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        set up a custom ant build independent from the maven 2 build
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        changed all tests from Junit 3 to Junit 4
      </action>
      <action dev="thierry" type="fix">
        fixed accuracy of PEF frame
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Aude Privat">
        fixed configuration problems on Windows systems
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Sébastien Herbinière">
        fixed a reversed sign in solar radiation pressure
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="update" >
        Orekit supports the two different naming patterns for bulletins B provided by IERS
        on http://www.iers.org/ and http://hpiers.obspm.fr/eop-pc/.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        the predefined times scales (TAI, UTC ...) are now built using a factory. The various
        XXXScale.getInstance() methods defined in each predefined time scales classes
        are still available, but have been deprecated and will be removed in the future,
        they are replaced by TimeScalesFactory.getXXX().
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="update" >
        the Frame class was split into a FramesFactory class, dealing with the predefined
        reference frames, and a Frame class for the creation of new frames and the navigation
        through any frames tree. The Frame.getXXX() methods for the predefined reference
        frames are still available, but have been deprecated and will be removed in the future,
        they are replaced by FramesFactory.getXXX().
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add" >
        3 new predefined reference frames have been added in Orekit : MEME, TEME and PEF. They
        implement the classical paradigm of equinox-based transformations including the IAU-76
        precession model, the IAU-80 nutation model and the IAU-82 sidereal time model, with
        the capability to apply the nutation corrections provided by IERS through the EOP data
        files for better agreement with the IAU 2000 precession-nutation model.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        the ChronologicalComparator class is not a singleton anymore, this didn't really make sense
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed a state reset error: orbital state changed by event detectors like
        ImpulseManeuver were overwritten by other event detectors
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed stop date of analytical propagators (Keplerian and Eckstein-Heschler). They used to
        stop at the first event after target date when an event detector was set up, instead of
        stopping at the target date
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        the gravity coefficients for solar system bodies are now extracted from JPL files headers
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        the eventOccurred method in EventDetector interface and its various implementations
        has an additional parameter specifying if the switching function increases or
        decreases at event time. This allows simpler events identification has many switching
        functions have two switches (start/end, raising/setting, entry/exit ...). Note that
        this changes breaks compatibility for users that did implement their own events, but
        it is simple to deal with (simply add one parameter in the signature and ignore it)
        so its was considered acceptable.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Christophe Pipo">
        fixed an error occurring when DE406 JPL ephemerides were loaded before DE405 ones
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Sébastien Herbinière">
        fixed an error in EGM potential file loader
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        trigger exceptions when no data can be loaded
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        remove predefined leap seconds, they are not useful anymore since other
        parts of the library do need configuration data (solar system bodies) and
        since data configuration has been vastly improved
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added support for the ICGEM format for gravity fields
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        load gravity potential data using the same mechanism already used for Earth
        Orientation Parameters, UTC-TAI history and JPL ephemerides files
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="quinput and Kai Ruhl">
        re-activated a way to load data from the classpath using a
        data provider plugin.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a way to load data directly from network (either
        locally or through a proxy server) using a data provider plugin.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a small plugin-like mechanism to delegate data loading to a
        user-provided mechanism, thus enabling smooth integration in existing
        systems.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        updated to latest version of commons-math.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Silvia Ríos Bergantiños">
        added galician localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Guylaine Prat">
        improved javadoc comments in orbit classes.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        tidal corrections are now available for ITRF and TIRF frames. Both frames are
        provided in two versions, the standard one with tidal corrections and a stripped
        down one without tidal corrections. A cache/interpolation mechanism is used to
        keep the computation cost of tidal correction to a minimum. With this mechanism,
        the penalty to use tidal correction is slightly above 20% in run time for a
        transformation between GCRF and ITRF. A raw implementation without this mechanism
        would lead to a 550% penalty, or even a 1100% penalty if TIRF and ITRF parts were
        computed independently.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="4.0" date="2008-10-13"
             description="major upgrade with new features (GCRF and ITRF2005 frames, DE 405
             and DE 406 ephemerides support, improved and greatly simplified date/time support,
             vastly improved data configuration with zip files support, new tutorials, improved
             performances, more tests and all identified bugs fixed, new translation files for
             italian, spanish and norse.">
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix">
        The ephemeris produced by numerical propagator now checks date validity in
        propagate method.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        The EME2000/J2000 frame was slightly mis-oriented (about 20 milli arcseconds).
        It really was the GCRF frame. This has been fixed and now both the GCRF and
        the EME2000/J2000 are available.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Dates in UTC within leap seconds are now displayed correctly (i.e. a 61st
        second is added to the minute).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="quinput">
        Fixed an overflow error in AbsoluteDate that generated an exception when any
        attempts was made to print dates far away like AbsoluteDate.JULIAN_EPOCH or
        AbsoluteDate.MODIFIED_JULIAN_EPOCH.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Changed test configuration to always use a new JVM for each test. This prevents
        some false positive to be generated.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The GeodeticPoint constructor arguments has been reordered to reflect more
        traditional usage, latitude coming before longitude.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The low accuracy Sun model based on Newcomb theory and the Moon model based
        on Brown theory have been withdrawn as they are superseded by the support of JPL
        DE 405 binary ephemerides files.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The ThirdBody abstract class has been removed and its specific method
        getMu has been moved up into CelestialBody interface and
        renamed getGM.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Improved external data configuration. The java property is now called
        orekit.data.path and is a colon or semicolon separated path containing
        directories or zip archives, themselves containing embedded directories
        or zip archives and data files. This allows easy roll-out of system-wide
        configuration data that individual users can override by prepending their
        own data trees in front of the path. This also allows simple configuration
        since many data files can be stored in easy to handle zip archives.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Renamed the iers package into data, as it is not IERS specific anymore. Some
        classes where also moved out of the package and into the frame and time
        package and their visibility reduced to package only. This improves decoupling
        and reduces clutter on users by limiting the number of visible classes.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The performance of IAU-2000 precession-nutation model computation has been
        tremendously improved, using a combined caching and interpolation approach. The
        simplified model (which was quite inaccurate in version 3.1) has therefore been
        removed as it was not needed anymore.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The ITRF 2005 frame is now supported instead of the older ITRF 2000 frame. The
        Earth Orientation Parameters data handling classes have been updated to match
        this change and read the new file format provided by IERS.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The J2000 frame has been renamed as EME2000 as this name seems to be more
        widely accepted and reduces confusion with the J2000.0 epoch. The
        Frame.getJ2000() method is still available, but has been deprecated
        and will be removed in the future.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Changed TimeScale from base abstract class to interface only.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Renamed some classes for better understanding: ChunkedDate is now DateComponents,
        ChunkedTime is now TimeComponents, ChunksPair is now DateTimeComponents. The
        getChunks method from AbsoluteDate as also been renamed into getComponents accordingly.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        Added new tutorials.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added predefined local orbital frames: the (t, n, w) frame aligned with velocity
        and the (q, s, w) frame aligned with position.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a predefined detector for altitude crossing events.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added methods to get zenith, nadir, north, south, east and west direction for
        any GeodeticPoint.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Silvia Ríos Bergantiños">
        Added spanish localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Espen Bj&#248;rntvedt">
        Added norse localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Francesco Coccoluto">
        Added italian localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Derek Surka">
        Added support for mean motion first and second derivatives fields in TLE.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to rebuild the two lines of TLE instances.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Derek Surka">
        Added constructor from already parsed elements for TLE.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a method to retrieve a body-centered inertial frame to the
        CelestialBody interface. As a consequence, thirteen new frames are
        predefined: Sun, Moon, planets and barycenters provided by JPL binary
        ephemerides.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Support for the JPL DE 405 and DE 406 binary ephemerides files has been added
        and a factory class SolarSystemBody uses these files to provide implementations
        of the CelestialBody interface for Sun, Moon, the eight solar system
        planets,the Pluto dwarf planet as well as the solar system barycenter and Earth-Moon
        barycenter points.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        The CelestialBody interface now provides velocity as well as position.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        A getCalls() method has been added to the NumericalPropagator class to count the
        number of calls to the differential equations computation method. This helps
        tuning the underlying integrator settings in order to improve performances.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        A lot more classes and interfaces are now serializable, to help users embed
        instance in their own serializable classes.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added predefined leap seconds to allow proper turn-key use of the library
        even without an already configured environment. All known leap seconds at
        time of writing (2008) are predefined, from 1972-01-01 to 2009-01-01 (the
        last one has been announced in Bulletin C 36 on 2008-07-04 and is not yet
        present in the UTC-TAI.history published file)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved user-friendliness of the time-scales by changing methods parameters
        types to more easily understandable ones.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved user-friendliness of the AbsoluteDate class by adding several
        new constructors and methods for common cases. It is in particular now possible
        to use offsets within a time scale, for example to build a date given as a
        fractional number of days since a reference date in UTC, explicitly ignoring
        intermediate leap seconds.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved the class handling date/time components: added a constructor to allow building
        from an offset with respect to a reference epoch, implemented Comparable interface and
        added equals and hashCode methods.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved the class handling date components: added a constructor to allow building
        from any reference epoch, not only J2000.0 (thus simplifying use of modified julian day),
        added getMJD() method, added several constants JULIAN_EPOCH, MODIFIED_JULIAN_EPOCH,
        FIFTIES_EPOCH, GPS_EPOCH, J2000_EPOCH and JAVA_EPOCH.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a new time scale: GPSScale.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added the changes page to the generated site.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="3.1" date="2008-07-16"
             description="This release is the first public release of Orekit."/>
  </body>
</document>
