<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- Copyright 2002-2016 CS Systèmes d'Information
  Licensed to CS Systèmes d'Information (CS) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  CS licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Orekit Changes</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="9.0" date="TBD" description="TBD">
      <action dev="luc" type="update" due-to="Maxime Journot">
        Use DerivativeStructure to compute derivatives for Range measurements.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Improved conversion speed from Cartesian coordinates to geodetic coordinates
        by about 15%.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="add">
        Replace OrbitFile interface with EphemerisFile, adding support for multiple
        ephemeris segments and the capability to create a propagator from an ephemeris.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed thread-safety issues in DTM2000 model.
        Fixes issue #258.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        Added JB2008 atmosphere model.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        Added NRLMSISE-00 atmosphere model.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Hao Peng">
        Fixed outliers configuration parsing in orbit determination tutorial and test.
        Fixes issue #249
      </action>
       <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Greatly improved orbit determination speed when a lot of measurements are used
        (several thousands).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed ant build script to run Junit tests.
        Fixes issue #246.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Added a protection against zero scale factors for parameters drivers.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix">
        Fix AbsoluteDate.createMJDDate when the time scale is UTC and the date
        is during a leap second.
        Fixes issue #247
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed ant build script to retrieve Hipparchus dependencies correctly.
        Fixes issue #244.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="8.0" date="2016-06-30"
             description="Version 8.0 is a major release of Orekit. It introduces several new
             features and bug fixes as well as a major dependency change. New features introduced
             in version 8.0 are orbit determination, specialized propagator for GPS satellites
             based on SEM or YUMA files, computation of Dilution Of Precision and a new angular
             separation event detector. Several bugs have been fixed. A major change introduced
             with version 8.0 is the switch from Apache Commons Math to Hipparchus as the
             mathematical library, which also implied switching from Java 6 to Java 8.">
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Andrea Antolino">
        Improved accuracy of orbits Jacobians.
        Fixes issue #243.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Deprecated PropagationException, replaced by OrekitException.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix" due-to="Greg Carbott">
        Fix bug in restarting propagation with a ConstantThrustManeuver with an
        updated initial condition.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed a display error for dates less than 0.5ms before a leap second.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Use ParameterDriver with scale factor for both orbit determination, conversion,
        and partial derivatives computation when finite differences are needed.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Apply impulse maneuver correctly in backward propagation.
        Fixes issue #241.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added angular separation detector. This is typically used to check separation
        between spacecraft and the Sun as seen from a ground station, to avoid interferences
        or damage.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        All class and methods that were deprecated in the 7.X series have been removed.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Allow ICGEM gravity field reader to parse non-Earth gravity fields.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="add">
        Add methods for a integration step handler to tell if the start/end of the step is
        interpolated due to event detection. Also added ability to add a step handler in
        ephemeris mode.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix">
        Switch to a continuous Ap to Kp geomagnetic index conversion.
        Fixes issue #240.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        Added computation of Dilution Of Precision (DOP).
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        Added a specialized propagator for GPS spacecrafts, based on
        SEM or YUMA files.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Ported the new Hipparchus event handling algorithm to Orekit.
        This improves robustness in corner cases, typically when different
        event detectors triggers at very close times and one of them
        resets the state such that it affects the other detectors.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Simplified step interpolators API, replacing the setDate/getState
        pair with an interpolated state getter taking a date argument.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Switched from Apache Commons Math to Hipparchus library.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added an orbit determination feature!
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="add">
        Add EventHandler to record all events.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix">
        Fix exception during event detection using
        NumericalPropagator.getGeneratedEphemeris() near the start/end date of
        the generated ephemeris.
        Fixes issue #238
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="7.2" date="2016-04-05"
             description="Version 7.2 is a minor release of Orekit. It introduces several new
             features and bug fixes. The most important features introduced in version 7.2
             are handling of GLONASS and QZSS time scales, support for local time zones
             according to ISO-8601 standard, and finer tuning of short period terms in
             DSST propagator. Version 7.2 depends on version 3.6.1 of Apache Commons Math,
             which also fixes a bug related to close events detection.">
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added GLONASS and QZSS time scales. These time scales my be used in SP3-c files.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added parsing and displaying of local time according to ISO-8601 standard.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Added some protections against malformed SP3 files.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed Newcomb operators generation in DSST for high degree gravity fields.
        Fixes issue #237
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Improved tuning of DSST tesseral force models. Users can now tune max degree,
        max eccentricity power and max frequency in mean longitude for short
        period terms, as well as for m-daily terms.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Improved tuning of DSST zonal force models. Users can now tune max degree,
        max eccentricity power and max frequency in true longitude for short
        period terms.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed wrong continuous maneuver handling in backward propagation.
        Fixes issue #236
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="7.1" date="2016-02-07"
             description="Version 7.1 is a minor release of Orekit. It introduces several new
             features and bug fixes. The most important features introduced in version 7.1
             are a lot of new event detectors (field of view based detectors supporting any FoV
             shape, either on ground targetting spacecraft or on spacecraft and targetting
             ground defined zones with any shape, extremum elevation detector, anomaly,
             latitude argument, or longitude argument crossing detectors, either true, mean
             or eccentric, latitude and longitude extremum detectors, latitude and longitude
             crossing detectors), new event filtering capability based on user-provided
             predicate function, ability to customize DSST interpolation grid for short period
             elements, ability to retrieve DSS short periodic coefficients, removed some arbitrary
             limitations in DSST tesseral and zonal contribution, ability to set short period
             degree/order to smaller values than mean elements in DSST, vastly improved
             frames transforms efficiency for various Earth frames, three different types of
             solar radiation pressure coefficients, new tabulated attitudes related to Local
             Orbital Frame, smooth attitude transitions in attitudes sequences, with derivatives
             continuity at both endpoint, ground zone sampling either in tiles or grid with fixed
             or track-based orientation, derivatives handling in geodetic points, parsing of TLE
             with non-unclassified modifiers, support for officiel WMM coefficients from NOAA,
             support for tai-utc.dat file from USNO, tropospheric refraction model following
             Recommendation ITU-R P.834-7, geoid model based on gravity field, and use of the new
             Apache Commons Math rotation API with either Frame transform convention or vector
             operator convention. Numerous bugs were also fixed.
             Version 7.1 depends on version 3.6 of Apache Commons Math.">
      <action dev="thierry" type="add">
        Added tropospheric refraction correction angle following Recommendation ITU-R P.834-7.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a way to configure max degree/order for short periods separately
        from the mean elements settings in DSST tutorial.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed limitation to degree 12 on zonal short periods, degree/order 8 on
        tesseral short periods, and degree/order 12 for tesseral m-dailies in DSST.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed wrong orbit type in propagator conversion. The type specified by
        user was ignored when computing variable stepsize integrator tolerances.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Set up three different implementations of radiation pressure coefficients,
        using either a single reflection coefficient, or a pair of absorption
        and specular reflection coefficients using the classical convention about
        specular reflection, or a pair of absorption and specular reflection
        coefficients using the legacy convention from the 1995 CNES book.
        Fixes issue #170
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed wrong latitude normalization in FieldGeodeticPoint.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed blanks handling in CCSDS ODM files.
        Fixes issue #232
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed FramesFactory.getNonInterpolatingTransform working only
        in one direction.
        Fixes issue #231
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="add">
        Added Field of View based event detector for ground based sensors.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a getFootprint method to FieldOfView for projecting Field Of View
        to ground, taking limb of ellipsoid into account (including flatness) if
        Field Of View skims over horizon.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a pointOnLimb method to Ellipsoid for computing points that lie
        on the limb as seen from an external observer.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added an isInside predicate method to Ellipsoid for checking points location.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix">
        Support parsing lowercase values in CCSDS orbit data messages.
        Fixes issue #230
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a generic FieldOfViewDetector that can handle any Field Of View shape.
        The DihedralFieldOfViewDetector is deprecated, but the CircularFieldOfViewDetector
        which corresponds to a common case that can be computed more accurately and faster
        than the new generic detector is preserved.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a FieldOfView class to model Fields Of View with any shape.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a FootprintOverlapDetector which is triggered when a sensor
        Field Of View (any shape, even split in non-connected parts or
        containing holes) overlaps a geographic zone, which can be non-convex,
        split in different sub-zones, have holes, contain the pole...
        Fixes issue #216
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Carlos Casas">
        Added a protection against low altitudes in JB2006 model.
        Fixes issue #214
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Petrus Hyvönen">
        Enlarged access to SGP4 and DeepSDP4 propagators.
        Fixes issue #207
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed covariance matrices units when read from CCSDS ODM files. The
        data returned at API level are now consistent with SI units, instead of being
        kilometer-based.
        Fixes issue #217
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed DSST ephemeris generation.
        Fixes issue #222
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Vastly improved DSS short period terms interpolation.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Use new Rotation API from Apache Commons Math 3.6.
        This API allows to use both vector operator convention and frames
        transform convention naturally. This is useful when axis/angles are
        involved, or when composing rotations. This probably fixes one of
        the oldest stumbling blocks for Orekit users.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed state partial derivatives in drag force model.
        Fixes issue #229
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix">
        Fixed incorrect density in DTM2000 when the input position is not in ECI
        or ECEF.
        Fixes issue #228
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="add">
        Added capability to use a single EventHandler with multiple types of
        EventDetectors.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to customize interpolation grid in DSST, either using a fixed number
        of points or a maximum time gap between points, for each mean elements integration
        step.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added TabulatedLofOffset for attitudes defined by tabulating rotations between Local Orbital Frame
        and spacecraft frame.
        Fixes issue #227
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed wrong ephemeris generation for analytical propagators with maneuvers.
        Fixes issue #224.
      </action>
       <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed date offset by one second for TLE built from their components,
        if a leap second was introduced earlier in the same year.
        Fixes issue #225.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Allow parsing TLE with non-unclassified modifier.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        As a side effect of fixing issue #223, KeplerianPropagator and
        Eckstein-Hechler propagator are now serializable.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed missing additional states handling in ephemeris propagators
        created from analytical propagators.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed NPE and serialization issues in ephemeris propagators created
        from analytical propagators.
        Fixes issue #223.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed time scale issues in JPL ephemerides and IAU pole models.
        The time used for internal computation should be TDB, not TT.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed an issue with backward propagation on analytical propagator.
        During first step, the analytical interpolator wrongly considered the
        propagation was forward.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to retrieve short period coefficients from DSST as
        spacecraft state additional parameters. This is mainly intended
        for test and validation purposes.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Prevent small overshoots of step limits in event detection.
        Fixes issue #218.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Handle string conversion of dates properly for dates less than 1 millisecond
        before midnight (they should not appear as second 60.0 of previous minute but
        should rather wrap around to next minute).
        Partly fixes issue #218.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Enforce Lexicographical order in DirectoryCrawler, to ensure reproducible
        loading. Before this changes, some tests could fail in one computer while
        succeeding in another computer as we use a mix of DE-4xx files, some having
        a different EMRAT (81.30056907419062 for DE-431, 81.30056 for DE-405 and DE-406).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added EventEnablingPredicateFilter to filter event based on an user-provided
        enabling predicate function. This allow for example to dynamically turn some
        events on and off during propagation or to set up some elaborate logic like
        triggering on elevation first time derivative (i.e. one elevation maximum)
        but only when elevation itself is above some threshold.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Renamed EventFilter into EventSlopeFilter.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added elevation extremum event detector.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed ellipsoid tessellation with large tolerances.
        Fixes issue #215.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix" >
        Fixed numerical precision issues for start/end dates of generated
        ephemerides.
        Fixes issues #210
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added anomaly, latitude argument, or longitude argument crossings detector,
        either true, mean or eccentric.
        Fixes issue #213.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added latitude and longitude extremum detector.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added latitude and longitude crossing detector.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to convert between PVA and geodetic points with time derivatives.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Allow truncation of tiles in ellipsoid tessellation.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Propagator builders can now be configured to accept any orbit types
        and any position angle types in the input flat array.
        Fixes issue #208.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added smooth attitude transitions in attitudes sequences, with derivatives
        continuity at both endpoints of the transition that can be forced to match
        rotation, rotation rate and rotation acceleration.
        Fixes issue #6.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed attitudes sequence behavior in backward propagation.
        Fixes issue #206.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added factory methods to create AbsoluteDate instances from MJD or JD.
        Fixes issue #193.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Joris Olympio">
        Fixed wrong attitude switches when an event occurs but the active attitude mode
        is not the one it relates to.
        Fixes issue #190.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add"  due-to="Joris Olympio">
        Added a way to be notified when attitude switches occur.
        Fixes issue #190.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Ensure Keplerian propagator uses the specified mu and not only the one from the initial orbit.
        Fixes issue #184.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Improved frames transforms efficiency for various Earth frames.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Specify inertial frame to compute orbital velocity for ground pointing laws.
        Fixes issue #115.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Activated two commented-out tests for DTM2000, after ensuring we
        get the same results as the original fortran implementation.
        Fixes issue #204.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Javier Martin Avila">
        Fixed resetting of SecularAndHarmonic fitting.
        Fixes issue #205.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a way to sample a zone on an ellipsoid as grids of inside points.
        Fixes issue #201.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed an event detection problem when two really separate events occur within
        the event detector convergence threshold.
        Fixes issue #203.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Added protections against TLE parameters too large to fit in the format.
        Fixes issue #77.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Allowed slightly malformed TLE to be parsed.
        Fixes issue #196.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed overlapping issue in ellipsoid tessellation, typically for independent
        zones (like islands) close together.
        Fixes issue #195.
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="add">
        Added support to load WMM coefficients from the official model file
        provided by NOAA.
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix">
        Fixed javadoc of method "GeoMagneticField#calculateField(...)": 
        the provided altitude is expected to be a height above the WGS84 ellipsoid.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Added a simpler interface for creating custom UTC-TAI offsets loaders.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added support for USNO tai-utc.dat file, enabled by default, in
        addition to the legacy support for IERS UTC-TAI.history file
        which is still supported and also enabled by default.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a way to load TAI-UTC data from Bulletin A. Using this feature
        is however NOT recommended as there are known issues in TAI-UTC data
        in some bulletin A (for example bulletina-xix-001.txt from 2006-01-05
        has a wrong year for last leap second and bulletina-xxi-053.txt from
        2008-12-31 has an off by one value for TAI-UTC on MJD 54832). This
        feature is therefore not enabled by default, and users wishing to
        rely on it should do it carefully and take their own responsibilities.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added ellipsoid tessellation, with tiles either oriented along track
        (ascending or descending) or at constant azimuth.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Added customization of EOP continuity check threshold.
        Fixes issue #194.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="add">
        Added geoid model based on gravity field.
        Fixes issue #192.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Added automatic loading of Marshall Solar Activity Future Estimation data.
        Fixes issue #191.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Simplified Cartesian to ellipsoidal coordinates transform and greatly improved its performances.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed target point in BodyCenterPointing attitude.
        Fixes issue #100.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="7.0" date="2015-01-11"
             description="Version 7.0 is a major release of Orekit. It introduces several new
             features and bug fixes. New features introduced in version 7.0 are the complete
             DSST semi-analytical propagator with short-periodics terms (only mean elements
             were available in previous version), extension to second order derivatives for
             many models (Cartesian coordinates, angular coordinates, attitude modes, ...),
             bilinear interpolator in Saastamoinen model, attitude overriding during impulsive
             maneuvers, general relativity force model, geographic zone detector, and ecliptic
             frame.
             Several bugs have been fixed. One noteworthy fix concerns an inconsistency in
             Eckstein-Hechler propagator velocity, which leads to a change of the generated
             orbit type.">
      <action dev="hankg" type="add">
        Added bilinear interpolator and use it on Saastamoinen model.
        Implements feature #182.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Removed old parts that were deprecated in previous versions.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Updated dependency to Apache Commons Math 3.4, released on 2014-12-26.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed null vector normalization when attempting to project to ground a point already on ground.
        Fixes issue #181.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Lucian Barbulescu">
        Added Romanian localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed velocity inconsistency in orbit generation in Eckstein-Hechler propagator.
        The Eckstein-Hechler propagator now generated Cartesian orbits, with velocity
        computed to be fully consistent with model evolution. A side effect is that
        if users rebuild circular parameters from the generated orbits, they will
        generally not math exactly the input circular parameters (but position will
        match exactly).
        Fixes issue #180.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Improved acceleration output in Eckstein-Hechler model.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added projection of moving point (i.e. position and derivatives too) to
        ground surface.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a general 3 axes ellipsoid class, including a feature to compute
        any plane section (which result in a 2D ellipse).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added support for IERS bulletin A (rapid service and prediction)
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix">
        Fixed various issues in geomagnetic fields models:
        GeoMagneticField.getDecimalYear() returned a slightly wrong result: e.g. for 1/1/2005
        returned 2005.0020 instead of 2005.0, GeoMagneticFieldFactory.getModel() returned
        wrong interpolation near models validity endpoints, GeoMagneticField.transformModel(double)
        method did not check year validity. Added more unit tests and adapted existing tests for
        IGRF/WMM with sample values / results as they have changed slightly.
        Fixes issue #178.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Patrice Mathieu">
        Fixed closest TLE search. When filtering first from satellite ID and
        then extracting closest date, the returned satellite was sometime wrong.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Hank Grabowski">
        Allow attitude overriding during impulsive maneuvers.
        Fixes issue #176.  
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="add">
          Added general relativity force model.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Ioanna Stypsanelli">
        added Greek localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix">
          Fixed incorrect partial derivatives for force models that depend on satellite velocity.
          Fixes #174.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix">
          Fixed incorrect parameters set in NumericalPropagatorBuilder.
          Fixes #175.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Significantly reduced size of various serialized objects.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        PVCoordinatesProvider now produces time-stamped position-velocities.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Tabulated attitude provider can be built directly from time-stamped angular coordinates
        lists, in addition to attitudes lists.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added time-stamped versions of position-velocity and angular coordinates.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Daniel Aguilar Taboada">
        Fixed wrong rotation interpolation for rotations near π.
        Fixes issue #173.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Updated dependency to Apache Commons Math 3.3.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" due-to="Lucian Barbulescu, Nicolas Bernard">
        Added short periodics for DSST propagation.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a GeographicZoneDetector event detector for complex geographic zones traversal.
        Fixes issue #163.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix">
        Add Ecliptic frame. Agrees with JPL ephemerides to within 0.5 arcsec.
        Issue #166.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix">
        Fix cache exception when propagating backwards with an interpolated
        gravity force model.
        Fixes issue #169.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed parsing of dates very far in the future.
        Fixes issue #171.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Trigger an exception when attempting to interpolate attitudes without rotation rate
        using only one data point.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="fix">
        Fixed SpacecraftState date mismatch exception with some attitude providers.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed wrong scaling in JPL ephemeris when retrieving coordinates in a frame
        that is not the defining frame of the celestial body.
        Fixes issue #165.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" due-to="Lucian Barbulescu">
        Prepare generation of either mean or osculating orbits by DSST propagator.
        The short periodics terms are not computed yet, but there is ongoing work
        to add them.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" due-to="Lucian Barbulescu">
        Avoid recomputing Chi and Chi^2 in Hansen coefficients for tesseral.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" due-to="Nicolas Bernard">
        Added better handling of Hansen kernel computation through use of PolynomialFunction.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" due-to="Petre Bazavan">
        Compute Hansen coefficients using linear transformation.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed a non-bracketing exception in event detection, in some rare cases of noisy g function.
        Fixes issue #160.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed a missing reset of resonant tesseral terms in DSST propagation.
        Fixes issue #159.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Improved default max check interval for NodeDetector, so it handles correctly
        highly eccentric orbits.
        Fixes issue #158.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="6.1" date="2013-12-13"
             description="Version 6.1 is a minor release of Orekit. It introduces several new
             features and bug fixes. The most important features introduced in version 6.1
             are solid tides force model, including pole tide at user choice, and following
             either IERS 1996, IERS 2003 or IERS 2010 conventions ; ocean tides force model,
             including pole tide at user choice, loading a user provided model ; simultaneous
             support for IERS 1996, 2003 and 2010 for frames definition, which is very
             important to support legacy systems and to convert coordinates between older and
             newer reference systems ; greatly improved accuracy of celestial/terrestrial
             frames transforms (we are now at sub-micro arcsecond level for IERS 2003/2010,
             both with equinox based and Non-Rotating Origin, at a sub-milli arcseconds for
             IERS 1996, both with equinox based and Non-Rotating Origin) ; classical
             equinox-based paradigm and new non-rotating origin paradigm for inertial and
             terrestrial frames are now supported with all IERS conventions ; automatic
             conversion of IERS Earth Orientation Paramters from equinoxial to non-rotating
             paradigm ; support for CCSDS Orbit Data Message ; improved API for events,
             allowing separation of event detection and event handling (the older API is still
             available for compatibility) ; merged all the elevation related events, allowing
             to use both refraction model and antenna mask at the same time if desired ;
             new attitude mode based on interpolation on a table. Numerous bugs were also fixed.
             Version 6.1 depends on version 3.2 of Apache commons math.">
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Reduced number of calls to the g function in event detectors.
        Fixes issue #108.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed a spurious backward propagation.
        Fixes issue #107.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Improved error detection for numerical and DSST propagation for cases
        where user attempts to compute integrator tolerances with an orbit for
        which Jacobian is singular (for example equatorial orbit while using
        Keplerian representation).
        Fixes issue #157.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a method to get the number or calls to getNeighbors in the generic time stamped cache,
        to allow performing measurements while tuning the cache.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added high degree ocean load deformation coefficients computed by Pascal
        Gégout (CNRS / UMR5563 - GET).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Time scales are now serializable.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Nicolas Bernard">
        Improved DSST tesseral computation efficiency by caching Jacobi polynomials.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Daniel Aguilar Taboada">
        Fixed yaw steering attitude law, which didn't project spacecraft velocity correctly.
        Fixes issue #156.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to set the maximum number of iterations for events detection.
        Fixes issue #155.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added an attitude provider from tabulated attitudes.
        Fixes issue #154.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Hank Grabowski">
        Improved test coverage.
        Fixes issue #153.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Hank Grabowski">
        Merged all elevation detectors into one. The new detector supports all
        features from the previous (and now deprecated) ApparentElevationDetector
        and GroundMaskElevationDetector.
        Fixes issue #144.  
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Hank Grabowski">
        Added a DetectorEventHandler interface aimed at handling only the
        event occurrence part in propagation. This allows to separate the
        event detection itself (which is declared by the EventDetector interface)
        from the action to perform once the event has been detected. This also
        allows to avoid subclassing of events, which was cumbersome. It also allows
        to share a single handler for several events.
        The previous behavior with eventOccurred declared at detector level and
        subclassing is still available but is deprecated and will be removed in
        the next major release.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Christophe Le Bris">
        Fixed an indexing error in Harris-Priester model.
        Fixes issue #152.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a new force model for ocean tides in numerical propagation, including pole tides.
        Fixes issue #11.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Lucian Barbulescu">
        Fixed conversion from position-velocity to Keplerian, when the orbit is
        perfectly equatorial.
        Fixes issue #151.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a new force model for solid tides in numerical propagation, including pole tides.
        Fixes issue #10.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a way to select IERS conventions for non-rotating origin
        based ITRF.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Greatly improved accuracy of celestial/terrestrial frames transforms.
        We are now at sub-micro arcsecond level for IERS 2003/2010, both with
        equinox based and Non-Rotating Origin, at a sub-milli arcseconds
        for IERS 1996, both with equinox based and Non-Rotating Origin.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed missing nutation correction in Equation Of Equinoxes.
        Fixes issue #150.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed rate for TCB time scale.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added new definition of astronomical unit from IAU-2012 resolution B2.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed Date/Time split problem when date is a few femto-seconds before the end of the day.
        Fixes issue #149.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed overflow problem in TimeComponents.
        Fixes issue #148.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Separate parsing from using Poisson series.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Steven Ports">
        Added support for parsing CCSDS ODM files (OPM, OMM and OEM).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Flattened ITRF frames tree so all supported ITRF realizations (2005, 2000, 97, 93) share the same
        parent ITRF2008. Previously, the tree was 2008 &lt;- 2005 &lt;- 2000 &lt;- {93,97} and the reference dates
        for Helmert transforms were all different. We now use the parameters provided at epoch 2000.0 and
        with respect to ITRF2008 at http://itrf.ensg.ign.fr/doc_ITRF/Transfo-ITRF2008_ITRFs.txt.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed azimuth parameter in the TopocentricFrame.pointAtDistance method.
        Fixes issue #145.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix"  due-to="Matt Edwards">
        Fixed location of JAVA_EPOCH. As we now take the linear models between UTC and TAI
        that were used between 1961 and 1972, we have to consider the offset that was in
        effect on 1970-01-01 and which was precisely 8.000082s. Fixes issue #142.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Vastly improved performances for Poisson series computations. Poisson series are often
        evaluated several components together (x/y/s in new non-rotating paradigm, ∆ψ/∆ε in old
        equinox paradigm for example). As the components are built from a common model, they
        share many nutation terms. We now evaluate these shared terms only once, as we evaluate
        the components in parallel thanks to a preliminary "compilation" phase performed when
        the Poisson series are set up. This dramatically improves speed: on a test case based
        on x/y/s evaluations over a one year time span without any caching,  we noticed a
        more than two-fold speedup: mean computation time reduced from 6.75 seconds (standard
        deviation 0.49s) to 3.07 seconds (standard deviation 0.04s), so it was a 54.5% reduction
        in mean computation time. At the same time, accuracy was also improved thanks to the
        Møller-Knuth TwoSum algorithm without branching now used for summing all series terms.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        When UT1 time scale is used, it is now possible to choose which Earth Orientation
        Parameters history to use (formerly, only EOP compatible with IAU-2000/2006 was
        used, even for systems relying only on older conventions).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added Greenwich Mean Sidereal Time and Greenwich Apparent Sidereal Time
        to all supported IERS conventions (i.e. IERS 1996, IERS 2003 and IERS 2010).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Classical equinox-based paradigm and new non-rotating origin paradigm for
        inertial and terrestrial frames are now supported with all IERS conventions.
        This means it is now possible to use MOD/TOD/GTOD with the recent precession/nutation
        models from recent conventions, and it is also possible to use CIRF/TIRF/ITRF with
        the older precession nutation models from ancient conventions. Of course, all these
        conventions and frames can be used at the same time, which is very important to
        support legacy systems and to convert coordinates between older and newer reference
        systems.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added IERS 1996 in the list of supported IERS conventions.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added factory methods to compute arbitrary Julian Epochs (J1900.0, J2000.0 ...)
        and Besselian Epochs (B1900.0, B1950.0 ...) that are used as reference dates
        in some models and frames.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed non-bracketing exception while converting Cartesian points very close to equator into geodetic
        coordinates. Fixes issue #141.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="add" >
        Added getAngularVelocity() to PVCoordinates.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added back serialization for some ephemerides produced by integration-based propagators.
        The ephemerides produced by NumericalPropagator are always serializable, and the ones
        produced by DSSTPropagator may be serializable or not depending on the force models used.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed missing events detection when two events occurred at exactly the same time using an analytical
        propagator (like generated ephemerides for example). Fixes issue #138.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed data loading from zip/jar. A more streamlined architecture has been set up, and each zip entry
        now uses its own input stream. Closing the stream triggers the switch to the next entry, and duplicate
        close are handled gracefully. Fixes issue #139.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Improved event bracketing by backporting changes made in Apache Commons Math (may fix issues #110
        and #136, but we cannot be sure as neither issues were reproducible even before this change...).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed GTOD and Veis frame that did apply UT1-UTC correction when they should not (fixes issue #131).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Completely rewrote conversion from Cartesian to geodetic coordinates to improve
        numerical stability for very far points (typically when computing coordinates
        of Sun). Fixes issue #137.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="6.0" date="2013-04-23"
             description="Version 6.0 is a major release of Orekit. It introduces several new
             features and bug fixes. Several incompatibilities with respect to previous
             versions 5.x have been introduced. Users are strongly advised to upgrade to this
             version. The major features introduced in version 6.0 are the inclusion of the DSST
             semi-analytical propagator, an improved propagator architecture where all propagators
             can use events and step handlers, much better and faster gravity field force model,
             Jacobians availability for all force models, converters between different propagation
             models (which can be used to convert between mean and osculating elements), thread
             safety for many parts (mainly frames, but still excluding propagators) while still
             preserving caching for performances even in multi-threaded environments, time-dependent
             gravity fields, support for IERS 2010 conventions, support for INPOP and all DExxx
             ephemerides, new frames, new time scales, support for user-defined states in spacecraft
             state, availability of additional states in events, interpolators for many components
             like position-velocity, spacecraft state and attitude allowing to compute high order
             derivatives if desired, filtering of events, orphan frames, magnetic fields models,
             SP3 files support, visibility circles, support for Marshall Solar Activity Future
             Estimation of solar activity. Numerous bugs were also fixed. Version 6.0 now depends
             on version 3.2 of Apache commons math.">
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix" >
        Fixed conversion of mean anomaly to hyperbolic eccentric anomaly (fixes issue #135).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Extracted fundamental nutation arguments from CIRF frame. This allows both reuse of
        the arguments for other computations (typically tides), and also allows to use
        convention-dependent arguments (they are similar for IERS conventions 2003 and 2010,
        but have changed before and may change in the future).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed event g function correction when starting exactly at 0 with a backward
        propagation (fixes issue #125).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Error messages properties are now loaded directly in UTF-8.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to know which tide system is used in gravity fields (zero-tide,
        tide-free or unknown).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added orphan frame, i.e. trees that are not yet connected to the main
        frame tree but attached later on. This allows building frame trees
        from leaf to root. This change fixes feature request #98.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to filter only increasing or decreasing events. The filtering
        occurs a priori, i.e. the filtered out events do not trigger a search.
        Only the interesting events are searched for and contribute to computation
        time. This change fixes feature request #104.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add" >
        Added a semianalytical propagator based on the Draper Semianalytic
        Satellite Theory. The DSST accounts for all significant perturbations
        (central body including tesseral harmonics, third-body, drag, solar
        radiation pressure) and is applicable to all orbit classes.
        To begin with, only mean elements propagation is available.
      </action>
      <action dev="evan" type="update" >
        Greatly improved performance of time-stamped caches for data that is
        read only once (like UTC leap seconds history or EOP).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Additional states can now be used in events. Note that waiting for the
        fix for issue MATH-965 in Apache Commons Math to be been officially
        published, a workaround has been used in Orekit. This workaround
        implies that events that should be triggered based on additional equations
        for integration-based propagator will be less accurate on the first step
        (full accuracy is recovered once the first step is accepted).
        So in these corner cases, users are advised to start propagation at least
        one step before the first event (or to use a version of Apache Commons Math
        that includes the fix, which has been added to the development version as
        of r1465654). This change fixes feature request #134.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        AdditionalStateProviders can now be used for all propagators, not
        only analytical ones. Note that when both state providers and
        additional differential equations are used in an integration-based
        propagator, they must used different states names. A state can only
        be handled by one type at a time, either already integrated or
        integrated by the propagator (fixes feature request #133).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to store user data into SpacecraftState. User data are
        simply double arrays associated to a name. They are handled properly
        by interpolation, event handlers, ephemerides and adapter propagators.
        Note that since SpacecraftState instances are immutable, adding states
        generates a new instance, using a fluent API principle (fixes feature request #132).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to retrieve all additional states at once from a step interpolator.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed wrong orientation for ICRF and all IAU pole and prime meridians
        (a few tens milli-arcseconds). This error mainly induced an error in
        celestial bodies directions, including the Sun which is used in many
        places in Orekit (fixes bug #130).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added support for IERS conventions 2010. Note that Orekit still also
        support conventions 2003 in addition to conventions 2010. However, as
        IERS does not provide anymore data to link TIRF 2003 with ITRF, ITRF
        based on 2003 convention is not available. ITRF can only be based on
        either 2010 conventions for CIO-based paradigm or on 1996 conventions
        for equinox-based paradigm. 
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Atmosphere models now provide their central body frame.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added versions of angular coordinates and position-velocity that use
        any field instead of double (classes FieldAngularCoordinates and
        FieldPVCoordinates). This allows to compute derivatives of these quantities
        with respect to any number of variables and to any order (using DerivativeStructure
        for the field elements), or to compute at arbitrary precision (using Dfp for
        the field elements). Regular transforms as produced by frames
        handle these objects properly and compute partial derivatives for them.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Converted Cunningham and Droziner force models to use the API of the new
        partial derivatives framework, despite they STILL USE finite differences.
        These two force models are now considered obsolete, they have been
        largely superseded by the Holmes-Featherstone model, which can be used
        for much larger degrees (Cunnigham and Droziner use un-normalized
        equations and coefficients which underflow at about degree 90), which
        already provides analytical derivatives, and which is twice faster. It
        was therefore considered a waste of time to develop analytical derivatives
        for them. As a consequence, they use finite differences to compute their
        derivatives, which adds another huge slow down factor when derivatives are
        requested. So users are strongly recommended to avoid these models when
        partial derivatives are desired...
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added analytical computation of partial derivatives for third-body
        attraction.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added analytical computation of partial derivatives for constant
        thrust maneuvers.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Converted Newtonian force model to use the new partial derivatives
        framework.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Converted Holmes-Featherstone force model to use the new partial derivatives
        framework.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added analytical computation of partial derivatives for surface forces
        (drag and radiation pressure) for all supported spacecraft body shapes.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Streamlined the force models partial derivatives computation for numerical
        propagation. It is now far simpler to compute analytically the derivatives
        with respect to state and with respect to force models specific parameters,
        thanks to the new Apache Commons Math differentiation framework. 
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a new force model for central body gravity field, based on Holmes and Featherstone
        algorithms. This model is a great improvement over Cunningham and Droziner models. It
        allows much higher degrees (it uses normalized coefficients and carefully crafted
        recursions to avoid overflows and underflows). It computes analytically all partial
        derivatives and hence can be used to compute accurate state transition matrices. It is
        also much faster than the other models (for example a 10 days propagation of a low Earth
        orbit with a 1cm tolerance setting and a 69x69 gravity field was about 45% faster with
        Holmes and Featherstone than with Cunningham).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Improved gravity field un-normalization to allow higher degrees/order with Cunningham and
        Droziner models. Formerly, the coefficients computation underflowed for square fields
        degree = order = 85, and for non-square fields at degree = 130 for order = 40. Now square
        fields can go slightly higher (degree = order = 89) and non-square fields can go much
        higher (degree = 393 for order = 63 for example). Attempts to use un-normalization past
        the underflow limit now raises an exception.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Updated Orekit to version 3.1.1 of Apache Commons Math.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added support for time-dependent gravity fields. All recent gravity
        fields include time-dependent coefficients (linear trends and pulsations
        at several different periods). They are now properly handled by Orekit.
        For comparison purposes, it is still possible to retrieve only the constant
        part of a field even if the file contains time-dependent coefficients too.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Added a way to speed up parsing and reduce memory consumption when
        loading gravity fields. Now the user can specify the maximal degree
        and order before reading the file.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        The EGM gravity field reader did not complain when files with missing
        coefficients were provided, even when asked to complain.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed serialization of all predefined frames. This fix implied
        also fixing serialization of celestial bodies as the predefined
        ICRF frame relies on them. Note for both types of objects, only
        some meta-data are really serialized in such a way that at
        deserialization time we retrieve singletons. So the serialized
        data are small (less than 500 bytes) and exchanging many time
        these objects in a distributed application does not imply anymore
        lots of duplication.
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix" due-to="Yannick Tanguy">
        Throw an exception if the conversion of mean anomaly to hyperbolic
        eccentric anomaly does not converge in KeplerianOrbit (fixes bug #114).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Evan Ward">
        Removed weak hash maps in frames (fixes bug #122).
      </action>
        <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Bruno Revelin">
        Improved documentation of interpolation methods (fixes bug #123).
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix" due-to="Evan Ward">
        Make TIRF2000Provider class thread-safe (fixes bug #118).
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix" due-to="Christophe Le Bris">
        Correct spelling of the inner class QuadratureComputation (fixes bug #120).
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix" due-to="Evan Ward">
        Remove unnecessary synchronization in UT1Scale (fixes bug #119).
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix" due-to="Carlos Casas">
        Clear caches in CelestialBodyFactory when removing CelestialBodyLoaders
        (fixes bug #106).
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix" due-to="Yannick Tanguy">
        Fix loading of JPL ephemerides files with overlapping periods
        (fixes bug #113).
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix" due-to="Simon Billemont">
        Prevent initialization exception in UTCScale in case no user-defined
        offsets are provided. (fixes bug #111).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Evan Ward">
        Improved performance by caching EME2000 frame in AbstractCelestialBody
        (fixes bug #116).
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix" due-to="Evan Ward">
        Make TidalCorrections class thread-safe by using the new TimeStampedCache. 
        (fixes bug #117).
      </action>
      <action dev="tn" type="fix" due-to="Evan Ward">
        Convert position entries contained in SP3 files to meters instead of km
        (fixes bug #112).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added support for version 2011 of ICGEM gravity field format. Orekit
        still ignore the time-dependent part of these fields, though.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Greatly simplified CelestialBodyLoader interface, now it is not related
        to DataLoader anymore (which implies users can more easily provide
        analytical models instead of the JPL/IMCCE ephemerides if they want)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Use the new thread-safe caches and the new Hermite interpolation feature on
        Transform, Earth Orientation Parameters, JPL/IMCCE ephemerides, UTC-TAI
        history and Ephemeris to remove thread-safety issues in all classes using
        cache (fixes #3).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added Hermite interpolation features for position-velocity coordinates,
        angular coordinates, orbits, attitudes, spacecraft states and transforms.
        Hermite interpolation matches sample points value and optionally first derivative.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added an AngularCoordinates as an angular counterpart to PVCoordinates.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Transform now implements both TimeStamped and TimeShiftable. Note that this change
        implied adding an AbsoluteDate parameter to all transform constructors, so this
        is a backward incompatible change.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed wrong transform for 3D lines (fixes bug #101).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Upgraded support of CCSDS Unsegmented Time Code (CUC) to version 4 of the
        standard published in November 2010 (fixes bug #91), this includes support for
        an extended preamble field and longer time codes.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Francesco Rocca">
        Added a way to build TLE propagators with attitude providers and mass (fixes bug #84).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed numerical stability errors for high order gravity field in Cunningham model (fixes bug #97).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Yannick Tanguy">
        Fixed an error in radiation pressure for BoxAndSolarArraySpacecraft (fixes bug #92).
      </action>
      <action dev="thomas" type="add">
        Added models for tropospheric delay and geomagnetic field.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The existing general mechanism for shifting objects in time has been
        formalized as a parameterized interface implemented by AbsoluteDate, Attitude,
        Orbit, PVCoordinates and SpacecraftState.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Time scales are not serializable anymore (this induced problems for the UTC scale
        and its caching feature).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed TLE propagation in deep space when inclination is exactly 0 (fixes bug #88).
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add" due-to="Francesco Rocca">
        Added a package for spacecraft states to propagators conversion extending an
        original contribution for TLE (Orbit Converter for Two-Lines Elements) to all
        propagators.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Improved testing of error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Removed too stringent test on trajectory in TLE propagator (fixes bug #86).
      </action>      
      <action dev="thomas" type="fix">
      	Set the initial state for a TLEPropagator (fixes bug #85).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Improved testing of error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Updated IAU poles for celestial bodies according to the 2009 report and the
        2011 erratum from the IAU/IAG Working Group on Cartographic Coordinates and
        Rotational Elements of the Planets and Satellites (WGCCRE).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Removed code deprecated before 5.0.
      </action>
      <action dev="thomas" type="add">
        Added support for more recent JPL DExxx and INPOP ephemerides files (fixes feature #23).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed formatting of very small values in TLE lines (fixes bug #77).
      </action>
      <action dev="thomas" type="fix">
        Fixed formatting of TLE epoch (fixes bug #74).
      </action>
      <action dev="thomas" type="fix">
        Fixed performance issues when using the singleton UTCScale instance from
        multiple threads. Use a prototype pattern instead (fixes bug #33).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added J2 effect on small maneuvers model.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed attitudeProvider field masking in IntegratedEphemeris.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a tutorial to compute Earth phased, Sun synchronous orbits.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a fitter for osculating parameters, allowing conversion to mean parameters.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Made Greenwich mean and apparent sidereal time publicly visible in GTOD frame.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Made equation of equinoxes sidereal time publicly visible in TOD frame.
      </action>
      <action dev="thomas" type="update">
        Added more german translations for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Allow ClasspathCrawler and ZipJarCrawler data providers to work in
        OSGi environments by providing an explicit class loader (fixes bug #54).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Improved the small maneuvers analytical model to compute orbit Jacobian
        with respect to maneuver parameters.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Force impulse maneuver to preserve orbit type and orbit frame.
      </action>
      <action dev="thomas" type="add">
        Added sp3 file parser.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a method to compute frames transforms Jacobians in the Transform class.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed a problem with propagation over null or negative ranges.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a multiplexer for step handlers.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added init methods to step handlers and event handlers.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added an adapter propagator that can add small maneuvers to any propagator, including
        ephemeris based ones.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added an analytical model for the effect at date t1 of a small maneuver performed at date t0.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed a missing reinitialization of start date when state was reset in numerical propagator.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Added detection of attempts to create hyperbolic orbits as circular or equinoctial
        instances.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix">
        Fixed potential numerical failure in lightning ratio computation.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Simplified construction of atmosphere models, the Earth fixed frame is already present
        in the body shape, there was no need to pass a separate argument for it.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        Added Harris-Priester atmosphere model.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Changed the return value of eventOccurred method from an int to an enumerate.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix">
        Fixed frame for TLEPropagator (fixes bug #31).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added getters/setters for impulse maneuvers.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added getters/setters for attitude provider in all orbit propagators.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a method to compute visibility circles in TopocentricFrame.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added an equinox-based version of ITRF.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added getters for thrust, Isp and flow rate in constant thrust maneuvers.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Allow use of any supported Local Orbital Frames as the reference frame
        for LofOffset attitude modes.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added support for LVLH, VVLH and VNC local orbital frames.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed a performance bug implying that some frames reloaded all EOP history files
        each time a transform was computed (fixes bug #26).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added support for columns-based IERS Rapid Data and Prediction files (finals.daily, finals.data
        and finals.all), the XML version was already supported since a few months
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed numerical issue in eccentricity computation (fixes bug #25)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Changed step handling of abstract propagators, now they use a single step
        equal to the duration of the propagation in all cases except when a fixed step
        is requested in master mode. Previously, they arbitrarily used on hundredth of
        the Keplerian period as the step size, hence performing many steps even if not
        strictly required
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added propagation of Jacobians matrices in circular, Keplerian and equinoctial
        parameters, using either true, eccentric or mean position angles. Formerly,
        propagation of Jacobians matrices was possible only in Cartesian parameters
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to propagate additional state along with orbit in abstract
        propagators, as an analytical counterpart to the additional equations that
        can be integrated by numerical propagators
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed missing partial derivatives data in ephemerides produced by a numerical
        propagator despite it was set up to computed them (fixes bug #16)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Added a new much simpler way to log events occurrences all at once (or
        only a subset of the events if desired)
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add" >
        Added alternative default name for ICGEM files
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix" >
        Fixed EventState reset on propagation direction change (fixes bug #19)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed Jacobianizer so it can handle force models that do change the spacecraft mass,
        like ConstantThrustManeuver (fixes bug #18)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added Jacobians between orbital parameters and Cartesian parameters for all orbits
        types (including hyperbolic orbits), all angles types (mean, eccentric, true) and in
        both directions
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        Replaced the integers parameters used in orbit constructors (MEAN_ANOMALY, ECCENTRIC_ANOMALY ...)
        by a new PositionAngle enumerate for better value safety. The old public constants and the
        corresponding constructors are still available but are deprecated
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        Fixed ephemeris generation in numerical propagation. After getEphemeris has been
        called,  later calls to the numerical propagator did reset the already computed
        and returned ephemeris (fixes bug #14)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Bruno Revelin">
        Added support for the Marshall Solar Activity Future Estimation files
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        TLEPropagator now implements the Propagator interface, and hence can benefit from all
        events detection and mode handling features (fixes features request #4)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        improved events detection robustness, by decoupling events handling from adaptive step
        sizes in numerical integrators and  (fix contributed to Apache Commons Math) and from
        classical propagation in analytical and tabulated propagators. This implies the events
        will NOT reduce integration step sizes anymore, thus also increasing speed and in corner
        cases reducing local precision at event occurrence, reducing max step size is often
        sufficient to compensate for this drawback
      </action>
      <action dev="v&#233;ronique" type="add" >
        all propagators, including analytical ones or tabulated ones can now be used for
        event detection. Of course for tabulated propagators, setting up an event that
        would try to reset the state triggers an error when the event occurs
      </action>
      <action dev="v&#233;ronique" type="add" >
        propagation can now be done between two dates, regardless of the date of the initial state
      </action>
      <action dev="v&#233;ronique" type="add" >
        attitude can be specified either using a date only thanks to a new AttitudeLaw interface
        or using a date, a position-velocity provider and a frame (which can be any frame) thanks
        to a new AttitudeProvider interface, wrappers have been added to convert between the two
        interfaces. A side effect of this change is that LofOffset constructor now needs a reference
        to an inertial reference frame, otherwise the attitude woud be wrong if a non-inertial frame
        were passed to getAttitude, due to velocity composition (the computed LOF would not really
        be a LOF)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        the notion of quasi-inertial frames has been renamed as pseudo-inertial because
        quasi-inertial has a precise relativistic meaning that is not considered here. We
        only consider these frames to be suitable for Newtonian mechanics.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        the equinox based frames have been renamed to more standard names (MOD, and GTOD
        instead of MEME, and PEF). The implementation of TEME was also wrong (it was
        really a TOD), so now there are both a TOD with a proper name and a TEME with a
        proper implementation.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        celestial bodies now provide both an inertially oriented body centered
        frame and a body oriented body centered frame, the bodies managed by
        CelestialBodyFactory use the IAU poles and prime meridian definitions
        to build the two frames
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added the ICRF frame at the solar system barycenter
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added the ITRF93, ITRF97, ITRF2000 and ITRF2008 frames (previously, only
        the ITRF2005 frame was available)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a getPoint method to TopocentricFrame
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added the Galileo System Time Scales and the Galileo start epoch.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added the UT1, TCB and GMST time scales used in CCSDS Orbit Data Messages
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an error when parsing a date occurring during a leap second introduction
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed a dut1 interpolation error for the day just before a leap second introduction
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an error in JPL ephemerides: they are in TDB time scale
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an error in date creation/parsing for UTC dates which occur during a
        leap second
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed UTC time scale between 1961-01-01 and 1971-12-31 ; in this time range
        the offset between UTC and TAI was piecewise linear
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added an enumerate for specifying months in dates and for simplifying parsing
        of some data files
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        completed support for CCSDS Time Code Format (CCSDS 301.0-B-3) ; now in addition
        to ASCII Calendar Segmented Time Code which has been supported for a while,
        Orekit also supports CCSDS Unsegmented Time Code (CUC), CCSDS Day Segmented
        Time Code (CDS) and CCSDS Calendar Segmented Time Code (CCS)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a freeze method to the Frame and Transform classes, in order to build fixed
        frames from moving ones, this is useful for example to build a launch frame
        at launcher inertial navigation system reset time, or to build an equinox-based
        frame at a specific epoch
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an out of memory error when lots of temporary frames were created in loops
        and discarded
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        use the new FastMath class from commons-math instead of the standard java.util.Math
        class for increased accuracy and speed
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added support for the new bulletinB data published by Paris-Meudon observatory
        for IAU-1980 precession-nutation model (IERS has ceased publishing bulletinB
        files for both IAU-1980 precession-nutation model and IAU-2000
        precession-nutation model as of early 2010).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added support for the new XML files containing both bulletinA and bulletinB data
        published by IERS (both the finals and daily files are supported).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Orekit now depends on at least version 3.0 of Apache commons-math
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a way to list what data have been loaded through DataProvidersManager
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        PropagationException can now be created directly from OrekitException, thus simplifying
        wrapping lower Orekit errors in step handlers
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        improved exception propagation from low level java runtime and Apache commons-math libraries
        preserving initial error stack trace
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        changed exception localization framework to simplify messages handling
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        greatly improved AbsoluteDate accuracy by shifting epoch when needed and separating
        long/double computations to avoid too large offsets and numerical cancellations, it is
        now possible to still have an absolute date accurate to about 1.0e-13s after shifting
        it 10000 times by 0.1s steps
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an error in TopocentricFrame.getPVCoordinates: the coordinates returned were not the
        coordinates of the topocentric frame origin with respect to the specified frame, but were the
        coordinates of the specified frame origin with respect to the topocentric frame.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an errors in data loading in tutorials when one of the path in the classpath
        contained a space
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        improved CelestialBodyPointed attitude mode: the spin now correctly includes
        the coupling effect of the phasing reference
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an error in SpinStabilized attitude mode: the spin was reversed
        with respect to the specification
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        added a GroundMaskElevationDetector dealing with local physical mask for visibility
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        added an ApparentElevationDetector taking refraction into account in a terrestrial
        environment
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="update">
        enhanced DateDetector behaviour to allow adding new event dates on the fly
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix" due-to="Derek Surka">
        fixed an error in FramesFactory when getting ITRF2005 and TIRF2000 frames:
        ignoreTidalEffects was handled wrong.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        removed serialization of some cached data in frames
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed deserialization problems of frame singletons, they were not unique any more
      </action>
      <action dev="v&#233;ronique" type="add" >
        numerical propagation can now be done either using Cartesian parameters, circular
        parameters, equinoctial parameters, or Keplerian parameters (elliptical or hyperbolic)
        and using mean, eccentric or true position angles for the parameters where it is relevant.
        So there are now 10 possible configurations for state vector. This allows propagation
        of any kind of trajectories, including hyperbolic orbits used for interplanetary missions,
        or atmospheric re-entry trajectories
      </action>
      <action dev="v&#233;ronique" type="update" >
        completely revamped the partial derivatives matrices computation using the additional
        equations mechanism
      </action>
      <action dev="v&#233;ronique" type="add" >
        added a mechanism to integrate user-supplied additional equations alongside with
        orbital parameters during numerical propagation
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        use A. W. Odell and R. H. Gooding (1986) fast and robust solver for Kepler equation
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        keplerian and cartesian orbits now support hyperbolic orbits (i.e. eccentricity greater
        than 1, and in this case negative semi major axis by convention)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed an error in LofOffset attitude mode: the computed attitude was reversed
        with respect to the specification
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added an AttitudesSequence class which can handle several laws, only one of
        which being active at any time. The active law changes as switch events are
        triggered. This can be used for example to alternate between daylight attitude mode
        and eclipse attitude mode, or between normal observing mode and special modes
        for ground contact or maneuvers.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix" due-to="Bruno Revelin">
        fixed an error when crawling a classpath or a directory a zip file was found.
        This might lead to select an inappropriate data provider.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="5.0.3" date="2011-07-12"
             description="version 5.0.3 is a bug-fix release.">
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed a performance bug implying that some frames reloaded all EOP history files
        each time a transform was computed  (fixes bug #26).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Fixed a parsing bug in IERS Rapid Data and Prediction files for dates between 2000 and 2009.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="5.0.2" date="2011-07-11"
             description="version 5.0.2 is an interim release of Orekit with support for IERS
                          Rapid Data and Prediction files.">
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Added support for IERS Rapid Data and Prediction files finals.all, finals.data and finals.daily,
        for both IAU-1980 and IAU-2000 and with both columns and XML formats.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="5.0.1" date="2011-04-15"
             description="version 5.0.1 is a minor release of Orekit without any functional changes.
             The differences with respect to 5.0 are only related to packaging and deployement to
             maven central. There are NO bug fixes and NO evolutions.">
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        updated packaging to allow deployment to maven central.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="5.0" date="2010-05-06"
             description="version 5.0 is a major release of Orekit. It introduces several new
             features and bug fixes. Some slight incompatibilities with respect to previous
             versions have been introduced, but they should be easy to overcome to users. Users
             are strongly advised to upgrade to this version. The major points introduced in version
             5.0 are a very general PVCoordinatesProvider interface, a new shiftedBy method allowing
             many time-dependent instances (AbsoluteDate, Orbit, PVCoordinates, Attitude and SpacecraftState)
             to be slightly shifted in time using simple evolution models (keplerian for orbit, fixed
             angular rate for attitude, fixed translation for position/velocity), a redesign of the
             attitude interfaces and an experimental (read subject to change) numerical propagator
             able to compute jacobians of the state with respect to both initial state and force
             models parameters. Version 5.0 now depends on version 2.1 of Apache commons math.">
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        a new experimental numerical propagator has been added, in addition to computing
        the spacecraft state at target time, it also computes the partial derivatives of
        this state with respect to the initial state (one jacobian) and with respect to
        models parameters (another jacobian). The jacobians are integrated alongside with
        the state, using variational equations for better accuracy and numerical robustness.
        This will help further implementation of orbit determination or optimization
        algorithms. This code is still considered to be experimental as of 5.0 and the API
        could change in the future.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        a new SpacecraftFrame class has been added, taking into account orbit and
        attitude thanks to an underlying propagator. This allows to see the spacecraft just
        as another known geometrical object automatically handled and connected to all
        other frames. For an instantaneous view, Transform instances can also be built
        directly by SpacecraftState instances.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        frames can now be flagged as quasi-inertial or not; only quasi-inertial frames
        are suitable for defining orbits
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        the Topocentric frame now provides a way to retrieve the body shape on which the
        frame is defined
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="update">
        changed the way Veis 1950 frame is constructed.
        Now, its parent is the PEF frame with no EOP corrections applied.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="John Pritchard">
        fixed a parameters inversion in Earth Orientation Parameters for IAU-1980 models.
        The error could introduce up to a few meters error in position during transformations
        between TEME and MEME
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        factories have been introduced for handling all data formats. Their default configuration
        correspond to the legacy formats used in previous versions (IERS format for UTC-TAI, EOPC04
        and bulletins B for Earth Orientation Parameters, JPL format for celestial bodies ...).
        Users can now add support for their own formats if they want (for example if they prefer
        using bulletins A instead of EOPC04 and bulletins B, or if they have their own gravity
        field format ...). Consequences of these changes are that the SolarSystemBody and
        the PotentialReaderFactory classes have been deprecated (replaced by CelestialBodyFactory and
        GravityFieldFactory) and that TimeScalesFactory and FramesFactory have been extended. All these
        factories follow the same generic pattern.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        improved thread safety (however, Orekit is still NOT completely thread-safe).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        the loaders for gravity fields now can optionally allow missing coefficients (they will be
        replaced by 0.0 except c[0][0] which will be replaced by 1.0).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        the loader for gravity fields in the ICGEM format now support empty lines in the file
        (there is for example one blank line at the end of the file in the orekit-data zip archive).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added support for the GRGS gravity field files formats.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added a way to list the available satellite numbers in TLE files.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        improved TLE elements loading. Now TLE lines are loaded using the standard data loading
        mechanism (thus allowing loading from disk files, network, classpath ...), they can
        contain TLE for several objects in one file, and they may contain some non-TLE lines
        if desired.
      </action>
      <action dev="v&#233;ronique" type="add" >
        a new PVCoordinatesProvider interface has been created on top of several existing classes
        and interfaces (orbit propagator, celestial bodies, some moving frames ...). This is a
        major generalization that allows to use either satellites or celestial bodies in many
        algorithms (attitude pointing target, eclipses and field of view events ...)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        improved numerical propagator efficiency when used from an outside loop: the initial
        state is automatically set to the last state at propagation end, thus allowing to
        restart from here without recomputing everything
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added a reset feature in all propagators, allowing to reuse an already configured
        propagator for several different orbits
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed a mode handling error in NumericalPropagator: when a propagator was reused
        with a new mode setting, the previous step handlers were still used in addition to
        the new ones instead of replacing them
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed an interpolation error for orbits crossing the -PI/+PI singularity between
        entries in the Ephemeris class
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        KeplerianPropagator now preserve orbits types
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        AbsoluteDate, Orbit, PVCoordinates, Attitude and SpacecraftState instances can now all
        be slightly shifted in time using simple evolution models (keplerian for orbit, fixed
        angular rate for attitude, fixed translation for position/velocity). This is not a
        replacement for proper propagation but is useful for known simple motions or small
        time shifts or when coarse accuracy is sufficient
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        changed AttitudeLaw.getState signature to use complete orbit. This is an incompatible
        change introduced to fix a major bug in spin computation for some attitude laws. The laws
        for which orientation depends on satellite velocity have a spin vector that depends on
        acceleration. This can be computed only if complete orbit is available. This change
        should be simple to handle from a users point of view, as the caller generally already
        has the orbit available and attitude laws implementations can retrieve all the former
        parameters (date, position/velocity, frame) directly from orbit.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed spin rate computation errors in almost all attitude modes
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added a new simple linear attitude mode: FixedRate
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed an error in event detection: when two events were very close (for example a very
        short ground station visibility), the second one may be ignored despite the first one
        was detected.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed corner cases in event detection during orbit propagation, sometimes
        an already detected and handled event prevented the propagator to go further in time.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added an EventShifter wrapper allowing to slightly shift raw events in time. This is useful
        for example to switch an attitude mode from solar pointing to something else a few minutes
        before eclipse entry and going back to solar pointing mode a few minutes after eclipse exit.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        added a new AlignmentDetector.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add" >
        added a new EclipseDetector handling either umbra or penumbra entry and exit events.
      </action>
      <action dev="v&#233;ronique" type="add" >
        added new CircularFieldOfViewDetector and DihedralFieldOfViewDetector handling
        field of view entry and exit events for any type of target.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added an experimental implementation of a BoxAndSolarArray spacecraft model considering a convex
        body (either parallelepipedic or defined by a set of facets) and a rotating solar array, for
        accurate modeling of surface forces with attitude. Beware that this class is still considered
        experimental, so use it with care!
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        completely changed the RadiationSensitive and DragSensitive interfaces to be more comprehensive
        and handle properly lift and side force effects when used with non-symmetric spacecrafts/flux geometry
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Christelle Blandin">
        fixed denormalization of gravity field coefficients, the last coefficient
        was not initialized
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added a relative constructor and a getMomentum method to PVCoordinates
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a special implementation improving performances for the frequent case of identity transform
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        fixed forgotten radians to degrees conversions for inclination and RAAN in CircularOrbit.toString()
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a Constants interface including a few useful physical constants.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a way to build date components from week components (this can be used
        for scheduled operations with week-related periods)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added string parsing features for dates and times components supporting ISO-8601 formats
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Orekit is now packaged as an OSGi bundle
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        added some pieces of an UML model for the library (available in the source distribution)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        updated error message localization to be more consistent with Java exception. Now getMessage
        returns a non-localized message and only getLocalizedMessage returns a message localized for
        the platform default locale. A new getMessage(Locale) method has also been added to
        retrieve the message in any desired locale, not only the platform default one. The messages
        are also built and translated only when needed, so if an exception is triggered and
        never displayed, the message will never be built.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="4.1" date="2009-08-18"
             description="version 4.1 is an upgrade bringing some new features and fixing a
             few bugs. The equinox-based frames family with IAU1980 precession-nutation
             models that are still used by many legacy systems are now supported. This
             simplifies interoperability with legacy systems and helps migrating from this
             old frames family to the new CIO-based ones that is supported by orekit since its
             first versions. The data loading mechanism used to retrieve IERS data (Earth
             Orientation Parameters, UTC-TAI history) and JPL ephemerides is now also used
             to retrieve gravity potential files. This mechanism has also been vastly improved
             to support new use cases (loading from disk, from classpath, from network delegating
             loading to an external library ...). Another change is the addition of the TDB
             time scale. Some minor incompatibilities have been introduced but they are easy
             to solve for users, the explanations are provided in detailed changes report.">
      <action dev="aude" type="add" >
        added TDB time scale
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        the RadiationSensitive and DragForce interfaces now have an
        additional SpacecraftState parameter in all their get methods.
        This allows to implement models that take into account solar
        arrays rotation. Note that this changes breaks compatibility
        for users that did add their own implementations, but it is
        simple to deal with (simply add one parameter in the signature
        and ignore it) so its was considered acceptable.
       </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="James Housden">
        added german localization for error messages
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        added a feature allowing all tests to clear the already built reference
        objects (frames, time scales, solar system bodies ...) between each tests,
        thus removing the need to launch tests in separate JVMS. This allows to
        launch all tests directly from eclipse, and this speeds up maven tests by
        a factor 4 at least
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        set up a custom ant build independent from the maven 2 build
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        changed all tests from Junit 3 to Junit 4
      </action>
      <action dev="thierry" type="fix">
        fixed accuracy of PEF frame
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Aude Privat">
        fixed configuration problems on Windows systems
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Sébastien Herbinière">
        fixed a reversed sign in solar radiation pressure
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="update" >
        Orekit supports the two different naming patterns for bulletins B provided by IERS
        on http://www.iers.org/ and http://hpiers.obspm.fr/eop-pc/.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        the predefined times scales (TAI, UTC ...) are now built using a factory. The various
        XXXScale.getInstance() methods defined in each predefined time scales classes
        are still available, but have been deprecated and will be removed in the future,
        they are replaced by TimeScalesFactory.getXXX().
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="update" >
        the Frame class was split into a FramesFactory class, dealing with the predefined
        reference frames, and a Frame class for the creation of new frames and the navigation
        through any frames tree. The Frame.getXXX() methods for the predefined reference
        frames are still available, but have been deprecated and will be removed in the future,
        they are replaced by FramesFactory.getXXX().
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add" >
        3 new predefined reference frames have been added in Orekit : MEME, TEME and PEF. They
        implement the classical paradigm of equinox-based transformations including the IAU-76
        precession model, the IAU-80 nutation model and the IAU-82 sidereal time model, with
        the capability to apply the nutation corrections provided by IERS through the EOP data
        files for better agreement with the IAU 2000 precession-nutation model.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        the ChronologicalComparator class is not a singleton anymore, this didn't really make sense
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed a state reset error: orbital state changed by event detectors like
        ImpulseManeuver were overwritten by other event detectors
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        fixed stop date of abstract propagators (Keplerian and Eckstein-Heschler). They used to
        stop at the first event after target date when an event detector was set up, instead of
        stopping at the target date
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" >
        the gravity coefficients for solar system bodies are now extracted from JPL files headers
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        the eventOccurred method in EventDetector interface and its various implementations
        has an additional parameter specifying if the switching function increases or
        decreases at event time. This allows simpler events identification has many switching
        functions have two switches (start/end, raising/setting, entry/exit ...). Note that
        this changes breaks compatibility for users that did implement their own events, but
        it is simple to deal with (simply add one parameter in the signature and ignore it)
        so its was considered acceptable.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Christophe Pipo">
        fixed an error occurring when DE406 JPL ephemerides were loaded before DE405 ones
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Sébastien Herbinière">
        fixed an error in EGM potential file loader
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        trigger exceptions when no data can be loaded
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        remove predefined leap seconds, they are not useful anymore since other
        parts of the library do need configuration data (solar system bodies) and
        since data configuration has been vastly improved
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        added support for the ICGEM format for gravity fields
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update" >
        load gravity potential data using the same mechanism already used for Earth
        Orientation Parameters, UTC-TAI history and JPL ephemerides files
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="quinput and Kai Ruhl">
        re-activated a way to load data from the classpath using a
        data provider plugin.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a way to load data directly from network (either
        locally or through a proxy server) using a data provider plugin.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        added a small plugin-like mechanism to delegate data loading to a
        user-provided mechanism, thus enabling smooth integration in existing
        systems.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        updated to latest version of commons-math.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Silvia Ríos Bergantiños">
        added galician localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="Guylaine Prat">
        improved javadoc comments in orbit classes.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        tidal corrections are now available for ITRF and TIRF frames. Both frames are
        provided in two versions, the standard one with tidal corrections and a stripped
        down one without tidal corrections. A cache/interpolation mechanism is used to
        keep the computation cost of tidal correction to a minimum. With this mechanism,
        the penalty to use tidal correction is slightly above 20% in run time for a
        transformation between GCRF and ITRF. A raw implementation without this mechanism
        would lead to a 550% penalty, or even a 1100% penalty if TIRF and ITRF parts were
        computed independently.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="4.0" date="2008-10-13"
             description="major upgrade with new features (GCRF and ITRF2005 frames, DE 405
             and DE 406 ephemerides support, improved and greatly simplified date/time support,
             vastly improved data configuration with zip files support, new tutorials, improved
             performances, more tests and all identified bugs fixed, new translation files for
             italian, spanish and norse.">
      <action dev="pascal" type="fix">
        The ephemeris produced by numerical propagator now checks date validity in
        propagate method.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        The EME2000/J2000 frame was slightly mis-oriented (about 20 milli arcseconds).
        It really was the GCRF frame. This has been fixed and now both the GCRF and
        the EME2000/J2000 are available.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Dates in UTC within leap seconds are now displayed correctly (i.e. a 61st
        second is added to the minute).
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix" due-to="quinput">
        Fixed an overflow error in AbsoluteDate that generated an exception when any
        attempts was made to print dates far away like AbsoluteDate.JULIAN_EPOCH or
        AbsoluteDate.MODIFIED_JULIAN_EPOCH.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="fix">
        Changed test configuration to always use a new JVM for each test. This prevents
        some false positive to be generated.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The GeodeticPoint constructor arguments has been reordered to reflect more
        traditional usage, latitude coming before longitude.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The low accuracy Sun model based on Newcomb theory and the Moon model based
        on Brown theory have been withdrawn as they are superseded by the support of JPL
        DE 405 binary ephemerides files.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The ThirdBody abstract class has been removed and its specific method
        getMu has been moved up into CelestialBody interface and
        renamed getGM.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Improved external data configuration. The java property is now called
        orekit.data.path and is a colon or semicolon separated path containing
        directories or zip archives, themselves containing embedded directories
        or zip archives and data files. This allows easy roll-out of system-wide
        configuration data that individual users can override by prepending their
        own data trees in front of the path. This also allows simple configuration
        since many data files can be stored in easy to handle zip archives.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Renamed the iers package into data, as it is not IERS specific anymore. Some
        classes where also moved out of the package and into the frame and time
        package and their visibility reduced to package only. This improves decoupling
        and reduces clutter on users by limiting the number of visible classes.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The performance of IAU-2000 precession-nutation model computation has been
        tremendously improved, using a combined caching and interpolation approach. The
        simplified model (which was quite inaccurate in version 3.1) has therefore been
        removed as it was not needed anymore.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The ITRF 2005 frame is now supported instead of the older ITRF 2000 frame. The
        Earth Orientation Parameters data handling classes have been updated to match
        this change and read the new file format provided by IERS.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        The J2000 frame has been renamed as EME2000 as this name seems to be more
        widely accepted and reduces confusion with the J2000.0 epoch. The
        Frame.getJ2000() method is still available, but has been deprecated
        and will be removed in the future.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Changed TimeScale from base abstract class to interface only.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="update">
        Renamed some classes for better understanding: ChunkedDate is now DateComponents,
        ChunkedTime is now TimeComponents, ChunksPair is now DateTimeComponents. The
        getChunks method from AbsoluteDate as also been renamed into getComponents accordingly.
      </action>
      <action dev="pascal" type="add">
        Added new tutorials.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added predefined local orbital frames: the (t, n, w) frame aligned with velocity
        and the (q, s, w) frame aligned with position.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a predefined detector for altitude crossing events.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added methods to get zenith, nadir, north, south, east and west direction for
        any GeodeticPoint.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Silvia Ríos Bergantiños">
        Added spanish localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Espen Bjørntvedt">
        Added norse localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Francesco Coccoluto">
        Added italian localization for error messages.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Derek Surka">
        Added support for mean motion first and second derivatives fields in TLE.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" >
        Added a way to rebuild the two lines of TLE instances.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add" due-to="Derek Surka">
        Added constructor from already parsed elements for TLE.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a method to retrieve a body-centered inertial frame to the
        CelestialBody interface. As a consequence, thirteen new frames are
        predefined: Sun, Moon, planets and barycenters provided by JPL binary
        ephemerides.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Support for the JPL DE 405 and DE 406 binary ephemerides files has been added
        and a factory class SolarSystemBody uses these files to provide implementations
        of the CelestialBody interface for Sun, Moon, the eight solar system
        planets,the Pluto dwarf planet as well as the solar system barycenter and Earth-Moon
        barycenter points.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        The CelestialBody interface now provides velocity as well as position.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        A getCalls() method has been added to the NumericalPropagator class to count the
        number of calls to the differential equations computation method. This helps
        tuning the underlying integrator settings in order to improve performances.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        A lot more classes and interfaces are now serializable, to help users embed
        instance in their own serializable classes.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added predefined leap seconds to allow proper turn-key use of the library
        even without an already configured environment. All known leap seconds at
        time of writing (2008) are predefined, from 1972-01-01 to 2009-01-01 (the
        last one has been announced in Bulletin C 36 on 2008-07-04 and is not yet
        present in the UTC-TAI.history published file)
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved user-friendliness of the time-scales by changing methods parameters
        types to more easily understandable ones.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved user-friendliness of the AbsoluteDate class by adding several
        new constructors and methods for common cases. It is in particular now possible
        to use offsets within a time scale, for example to build a date given as a
        fractional number of days since a reference date in UTC, explicitly ignoring
        intermediate leap seconds.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved the class handling date/time components: added a constructor to allow building
        from an offset with respect to a reference epoch, implemented Comparable interface and
        added equals and hashCode methods.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Improved the class handling date components: added a constructor to allow building
        from any reference epoch, not only J2000.0 (thus simplifying use of modified julian day),
        added getMJD() method, added several constants JULIAN_EPOCH, MODIFIED_JULIAN_EPOCH,
        FIFTIES_EPOCH, GPS_EPOCH, J2000_EPOCH and JAVA_EPOCH.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added a new time scale: GPSScale.
      </action>
      <action dev="luc" type="add">
        Added the changes page to the generated site.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="3.1" date="2008-07-16"
             description="This release is the first public release of Orekit."/>
  </body>
</document>
